# Matthias Bachfischer

#### CURRICULUM VITAE

Munich, Germany

■ bachfischer.matthias@gmail.com | 🎓 bachfischer.me | 🖸 Bachfischer | 🛅 Bachfischer

# Summary\_

About to finish my studies in Data Science (M.Sc.) at The University of Melbourne. Prior to my studies, I worked as an IT Architect at BCG Platinion. I have a strong technical background in statistics & machine learning and deep business expertise in digital transformation topics.

# Skills

**Programming Languages** Proficient in Python, Java and R, Familiar with Go, JavaScript and C / C++

IT Certifications Certified SCRUM Master (PSM I), Certified Product Owner (PSPO I)

Software Frameworks

Various ML frameworks (PyTorch, Tensorflow), Apache Hadoop

## **Education**

#### The University of Melbourne

Melbourne, Australia

M.Sc. IN DATA SCIENCE - GPA: 4.0/4.0 (PRELIMINARY)

Mar. 2020 - Mar. 2022

- · Learned about advanced concepts in statistics, probability theory and machine learning
- · Carried out research on using pre-trained language models like BERT to detect the spread of fake news in online social networks
- · Implemented an autonomous agent based on Reinforcement Learning to compete in an Australian university competition
- Built a system to process data from very large graphs using Graph Convolutional Neural Networks
- · Title of final thesis: An Investigation Into the Effectiveness of Learned Indexes under Adversarial Settings

#### Ostbayerische Technische Hochschule Regensburg

Regensburg, Germany

B.Sc. in Business Information Technology - GPA: 4.0/4.0

Oct. 2014 - Feb. 2018

- · Learned various programming languages (Java, Javascript etc.), databases, computer networks and operating systems
- Evaluated the feasibility of applying machine learning in intrusion detection systems
- Title of final thesis: Success Factors in Business-Managed IT

### **Universidad de Buenos Aires**

Buenos Aires, Argentina

LICENCIATURA EN ANÁLISIS DE SISTEMAS - OVERALL GRADE: 10/10

Mar. 2016 - Jul. 2016

• Completed a semester abroad as an exchange student in the Faculty of Engineering (Facultad de Ingeniería)

#### Industrie- und Handelskammer Regensburg

Regensburg, Germany

IT SPECIALIST - SYSTEM INTEGRATION - OVERALL GRADE: 92/100

Jul. 2013 - Jan. 2017

· Received professional training as part of the integrated degree program at KRONES AG (parallel to B.Sc.)

# Work Experience \_\_\_\_\_

#### **BCG Platinion GmbH**

Munich, Germany

IT ARCHITECT & VISITING ASSOCIATE

Jul. 2018 - Mar. 2020

- Designed and led the implementation of a cloud-based real-time data analytics platform for a leading German automotive OEM to process and analyze streaming data from connected cars
- Developed a target IT architecture to enable implementation of manufacturing analytics use cases for a large automotive supplier as part of their Industry 4.0 initiative
- Advised various companies from Industrial Goods & Automotive sector on digital transformation & IT strategy
- Led cross-functional teams during the development of digital platforms (full-stack)

INTEGRATED DEGREE PROGRAM - INFORMATION SYSTEMS

Neutraubling, Germany

Jul. 2013 - Feb. 2018

Aug. 2015 - Sept. 2015

- Implemented various IoT use cases on a Apache Hadoop Big Data Platform
- Redefined the software- and requirements engineering processes at KRONES

KRONES do Brasil São Paulo, Brazil

- Performed the migration of a stand-alone e-mail system to centrally hosted system based on MS Exchange
- Collaborated with the local IT staff to to set-up IT support procedures for Brazilian users

**KRONES AG** 

INTERNSHIP

# **Academic Experience**

#### King Abdullah University of Science and Technology

Thuwal, Saudi-Arabia

VISITING STUDENT

Apr. 2018 - Jul. 2018

- · Published a paper on applying Machine Learning techniques to classify toxic comments in online social networks
- Developed a large-scale dataset-driven search engine for scientific publications

#### Java Programming Lecture - Ostbayerische Technische Hochschule Regensburg

Regensburg, Germany

TEACHING ASSISTANT

Oct. 2017 - Feb. 2018

- Teaching assistant for Java Programming lecture ("Programming 2")
- · Responsible for weekly programming exercises with first-year students

## Honors & Awards\_

2016 **Scholarship**, German Academic Scholarship Foundation

Bonn, Germany

2020 Study Abroad Scholarship, German Academic Exchange Service

Bonn, Germany

# **Publications**

#### Success Factors in Business-Managed IT

Berlin, Germany

SKILL - STUDIERENDENKONFERENZ INFORMATIK

Sept. 2018

• Presented a research paper from a case study analysis of critical success factors in Business-Managed IT (i.e. Shadow-IT systems that are operated overtly and with support of the IT organization)

#### **Offensive Comment Classification on German Language Microposts**

Vienna, Austria

GERMEVAL 2018 - SHARED TASK ON THE IDENTIFICATION OF OFFENSIVE LANGUAGE

Sept. 2018

 Presented the participation of the KAUST Laboratory for Machine Intelligence and kNowledge Engineering (MINE) at the GermEval 2018 shared task (research paper + poster)

# Languages\_

German, maternal language	native speaker
English, excellent command	Level C2 (CEFR)
Spanish, very good command	Level C1 (CEFR)
Portuguese, good command	Level B2 (CEFR)
Arabic, working knowledge	Level B1 (CEFR)
Chinese, basic knowledge	Level A1 (CEFR)

# Extracurricular Activity \_\_\_\_\_

## **International Negotiating Skills**

Regensburg, Germany

Additional Training

Oct. 2015 - Jul. 2017

· Studied theoretical frameworks for cross-cultural studies and received advice on how to act in an international environment

#### Campus Asyl - Association to support refugees in Germany

Regensburg, Germany

MENTOR

Mar. 2017 - Aug. 2017

· Mentored and provided assistance to refugees studying for a university degree at OTH Regensburg